<document>

	<properties>
		<author email="kit@objectlab.co.uk">Benoit Xhenseval</author>
		<title>DateCalc Common</title>
	</properties>

	<head>
		<meta name="description" content="ObjectLab Kit offers free and open source Date calculators, released under the business-friendly Apache 2.0 license." />
		<meta name="keywords" content="Date calculator, IMM Dates, Period Calculator, Financial Calendar, Business Calendar, java, open source" />
		<meta name="Subject" content="Date Calculators" />
		<meta name="Copyright" content="ObjectLab Financial Ltd" />
		<meta name="Language" content="English" />
		<meta name="Designer" content="ObjectLab Financial Ltd" />
		<meta name="Distribution" content="Global" />
		<meta name="robots" content="ALL" />
		<meta name="Revisit-After" content="20 Days" />
	</head>

	<body>

		<section name="FX Calc Introduction">
			<p>The FX Calc package provides classes for handling Currencies and Rates within the Foreign Exchange business. The package requires JDK8.</p>
			<p>The FX Calculator is created via a FxRateCalculatorBuilder so that the FxRateCalculator can be immutable for a given set of parameters and rates
				(unless you provide a BaseFxRateProvider).</p>
		</section>

		<section name="Ways to import Base Rates">
			<p>The FX Calculator requires Base Rates to return rates, inverse rates or cross rates. There are 3 ways to import rates via the
				FxRateCalculatorBuilder</p>
			<ol>
				<li>addRateSnapshot(FxRate rate): add the rate to an internal map per CurrencyPair, an immutable map will be given to the Calculator so the bases
					rates will NOT change.</li>
				<li>ratesSnapshot(Collection&lt;FxRate&gt; rates): add a collection of rates to an internal map per CurrencyPair, an immutable map will be given
					to the Calculator so the bases rates will NOT change.</li>
				<li>baseFxRateProvider(BaseFxRateProvider) You then control when the Base Rates change, the Calculator will call the required CurrencyPair you
					either every time or once (if cacheBaseRates is true).</li>
			</ol>
		</section>
		<section name="FXRate">
			<p>
				Once you have an
				<a href="../apidocs/net/objectlab/kit/fxcalc/FxRate.html">FXRate</a>
				, you can call:
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>getBid: bid (amount the quoter would buy Ccy1 for a given amount of Ccy2).</li>
				<li>getAsk: ask (amount the quoter would sell Ccy1 for a given amount of Ccy2).</li>
				<li>getMid: (bid+ask)/2</li>
				<li>convertAmountUsingBidOrAsk: Given a monetary amount in the original currency, calculate the resulting amount in the other currency, using BID
					or ASK.</li>
				<li>getPaymentAmountForBuying: to get the amount you would get by buying a currency amount.</li>
				<li>getReceiptAmountForSelling: to get the amount you would get by selling a currency amount.</li>
			</ul>
		</section>

		<section name="Example">
			<script src="https://gist.github.com/benoitx/6261e7f299dbd62823b9.js"></script>
		</section>

	</body>

</document>